<section id="ctrl-interface" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <title>Calling by Interface</title>

<section><title>Interfaces</title>

  <para>When applets make use of a control, they are interested in its
    functionality, not its particular implementation. It doesn't matter which
    control gets loaded as long as the control does exactly what was expected.
    </para>

  <para>The functionality is described by <emphasis>interfaces</emphasis>
    and several implementations of an interface can exist. However, control
    authors have to make sure that two different implementations of the same
    interface provide the same functionality.</para>

</section>


<section><title>Unique Identifiers</title>

  <para>To avoid confusion and incompatibility problems, interface identifiers
    have to be globally unique. You don't have to worry about this requirement,
    however, because <application>gDesklets</application> takes care about this
    for you. It determines the identifier for
    each interface and makes sure that changes in an interface lead to a
    different unique identifier.</para>

  <para>The interface identifiers are made up of a human-readable name given
    by the interface's author, and a random-looking string. That string is
    based on a checksum of the interface and is affected by all changes to the
    interface, except for changes in comments.</para>

  <para>The identifiers might look intimidating at first, but there is no magic
    behind them and the only occasion when you get into touch with them is when
    you want to <link linkend="dsp-tag-control">load a control</link> in
    an applet. In that case, just use copy&amp;paste.</para>

  <para>Examples for interface identifiers are:</para>
  <programlisting>
ICalendar:cfw9o85ptery8egvoff6ijswc
ISystem:4i4p0jtvdz87qx44x2dm97ltj
ITime:9y703dqtfnv4w373caserz68r
  </programlisting>

  <para>They can be looked up in the
    <application>gdesklets-shell</application>, or by using the tool
    <application>test-control.py</application>. There's no need to take care
    about the identifier while writing a control.</para>

</section>

</section>
