<section id="layout-units" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <title>Units</title>

<section><title>Why Pixels are Bad</title>

  <para>In the old days, every computer screen was <literal>640 x 480</literal>
    pixels in size. An application with a pixel-based layout thus looked the
    same on all screens. Nowadays, however, common screen resolutions range
    from <literal>800 x 600</literal> pixels up to <literal>1600 x 1200</literal>
    pixels or even more. Of course, a pixel-based layout would look the same
    on all screens, but a layout designed for a <literal>800 x 600</literal>
    screen would be unreadably small on a <literal>1600 x 1200</literal> screen.
    </para>

  <para>Some resolutions don't even have a near-to-square pixel aspect ratio,
    and pixel-based layouts could look distorted.</para>

  <para>For truly resolution-independent layouts, you cannot work with pixel
    values. Instead, classical units such as centimeters, inches, or DTP
    points become useful. And, of course, <application>gDesklets</application>
    supports all of these.</para>

</section>



<section><title>Layouting with Units</title>

  <para>Every geometry property, such as the
    <property>x</property>, <property>y</property>, <property>width</property>,
    and <property>height</property> properties accept unit-based values. If the
    unit is omitted, pixels are used instead.</para>

  <para>The units supported by the <application>gDesklets</application> platform
    are:</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem><literal>cm</literal> - centimeters</listitem>
    <listitem><literal>in</literal> - inches</listitem>
    <listitem><literal>pt</literal> - DTP points (1 pt = 1/72 inch)</listitem>
    <listitem><literal>%</literal> - percentage of the size of the parent
                                     container element</listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <note>
    <para>The correct scaling factor for transforming into pixels is computed
      from the DPI setting of the X server. For good results, the DPI value
      has to be set correctly. Some display managers, e.g.
      <application>kdm</application>, are known to set a hardcoded value of
      100 dpi by default, which results in wrong scaling on most screens.</para>
  </note>

</section>


</section>
