<section id="tutor-tutor"  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <title>Tutorial Meta-Tutorial</title>

<para>by Martin Grimme</para>


<section><title>Introduction</title>

  <para>You can contribute to the tutorials chapter by writing new tutorials.
    This meta-tutorial shows you how to write compliant tutorials for this
    book.</para>
     
</section>



<section><title>DocBook</title>

  <para>DocBook is a widely used standard for writing documentation. It is a
    semantic markup language based on SGML. Recently, DocBook has been ported
    to XSLT stylesheets, so that any XSLT processor can process DocBook sources.
    The XSLT stylesheets we are using for generating HTML pages are those of
    the <application>yelp</application> project, because they are fast and
    produce good output.</para>

  <para>It's not the purpose of this tutorial to teach you DocBook. There are
    plenty of other tutorials available, which do a much better job at that.
    Here is a collection of resources to get you started with DocBook:</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem><ulink url="http://www.docbook.org"/> - The home of DocBook. You
      can find lots of information and documentation there.</listitem>
    <listitem><ulink url="http://docbook.sourceforge.net"/> - The DocBook Open
      Repository is the official home of the DocBook stylesheets.</listitem>
    <listitem><ulink url="http://www.docbook.org/tdg/en/html/docbook.html"/> -
      DocBook: The Definitive Guide. The name says it all. This is the online
      version of the most comprehensive DocBook book out there by
      Norman Walsh and Leonard Muellner.</listitem>
    <listitem><ulink url="http://developer.gnome.org/projects/gdp/handbook/gdp-handbook/index.html"/> -
      GNOME Handbook of Writing Software Documentation. This online book is a
      good source of information for writing software documentation with
      DocBook.</listitem>
    <listitem><ulink url="http://www.bartleby.com/141/"/> - The Elements of
      Style. This book is about good writing style.</listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

</section>



<section><title>Template</title>

  <para>To make stuff look uniform, please use the provided template for
    writing tutorials. You can copy and paste it into a new file from below:
    </para>

  <literallayout><xi:include href="tutor-TEMPLATE.xml" parse="text"/></literallayout>

  <para>The filename must start with "<filename>tutor-</filename>" and have the
    extension "<filename>.xml</filename>". After the hyphen, you include the
    (abbreviated) name of your tutorial. This name must be unique within the
    whole book. The same name with the "<literal>tutor-</literal>" prefix goes
    into the <property>id</property> attribute in the <command>section</command>
    tag in the first line of the document.</para>

</section>



<section><title>Screenshots</title>

  <para>A picture is worth a thousand words. Screenshots (and diagrams) help you
    illustrate what you're talking about. Please make good use of them because
    the reader will appreciate it.</para>

  <para>Screenshots can be included in DocBook like this:</para>

  <programlisting><![CDATA[
<screenshot>
  <mediaobject>
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref="gfx/my-image" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>
</screenshot>
  ]]></programlisting>

  <para>Please note that the filename does not get the suffix here. The file
    itself has the <filename>.png</filename> suffix, of course. The included
    files have to be in the PNG format (GIF used to be non-free and is now
    deprecated, and JPEG isn't free either).</para>

  <para>The filename of the screenshot must be unique within the book, too.
    It is recommended to start all filenames with the (abbreviated) name of
    your tutorial.</para>

</section>



<section><title>Showing XML</title>

  <para>In a tutorial for <application>gDesklets</application>, it's often
    necessary to show example code which is XML. Example code can be
    displayed with the <command>&lt;programlisting&gt;</command> tag:</para>

  <programlisting><![CDATA[
<programlisting>

  ...

</programlisting>
  ]]></programlisting>

  <para>A problem, however, is that the XML code of course uses characters
    which are reserved by XML, such as "&lt;" and "&gt;". You can get around
    this limitation by putting the example into a CDATA section:</para>

  <programlisting><![CDATA[
<programlisting><![CDATA[

  ...

]]>]]&gt;<![CDATA[</programlisting>
  ]]></programlisting>

  <para>There remains only one problem: CDATA sections cannot be nested. So,
    what if your example contains CDATA sections as well?</para>

  <para>The solution is to split the CDATA section into two CDATA sections
    at the point where the CDATA section in the example code ends:</para>

  <programlisting><![CDATA[
<programlisting><![CDATA[

  <![CDATA[ ... ]]>]]&gt;<![CDATA[

]]>]]&gt;<![CDATA[</programlisting>
  ]]></programlisting>

  <para>must be written as</para>

  <programlisting><![CDATA[
<programlisting><![CDATA[

  ...
  <![CDATA[ ... ]]>]]&gt;]]&amp;gt;&lt;![CDATA[<![CDATA[
  
]]>]]&gt;<![CDATA[</programlisting>
  ]]></programlisting>

  <para>This might look confusing at first, but the simple rule is that every
    occurrence of "<literal>]]&gt;</literal>" has just to be extended with
    "<literal>]]&amp;gt;&lt;![CDATA[</literal>".</para>

</section>



<section><title>Previewing Your Work</title>

  <para>To preview the new tutorial file, you have to embed it into a valid
    DocBook file. The tutorial file is just a section and not a complete
    DocBook file.</para>

  <para>The easiest way to embed it into a DocBook file is by getting the
    DocBook sources of this book from CVS and include your file in the
    tutorials chapter.</para>

  <para>You can retrieve the DocBook sources like this:</para>

  <screen>
    <prompt>$> </prompt><userinput>export CVSROOT=:pserver:anonymous@anoncvs.gnome.org/cvs/gnome</userinput>
    <prompt>$> </prompt><userinput>cvs login</userinput>
    (press <keycap>Enter</keycap> when asked for a password)
    <prompt>$> </prompt><userinput>cvs co gdesklets/doc/book</userinput>
  </screen>

  <para>Then you can include your tutorial in the file
    <filename>tutor.xml</filename> using XInclude like this:</para>

  <programlisting><![CDATA[
...

  <xi:include href="tutor-xml.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="tutor-hello.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="tutor-canvas.xml"/>
  ...
  <xi:include href="tutor-mytutorial.xml"/>

...
  ]]></programlisting>

  <para>The book can be previewed with the <application>yelp</application> tool
    of the <application>GNOME</application> desktop:</para>

  <screen>
    <prompt>$> </prompt><userinput>yelp ghelp://$PWD/book.xml</userinput>
  </screen>

  <para>The script <filename>make-html.sh</filename> can be called to convert
    the DocBook files to HTML using the <application>yelp</application>
    stylesheets (<application>yelp</application> must be installed):</para>

  <screen>
    <prompt>$> </prompt><userinput>./make-html.sh book.xml output</userinput>
  </screen>

  <para>The book can then be found in <filename>output/index.html</filename>.
    </para>
</section>

</section>
