<section id="layout-mistakes" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <title>Avoid Common Mistakes</title>

  <para>The layouting model used by <application>gDesklets</application> is based
  on nesting boxes. While this approach is highly flexible, yet easy to understand,
  there can be cases where the result might not look as expected. This section tries
  to explain some common mistakes and show why the result does look as it looks.</para>
  


<section><title>Containers Collapse</title>

  <para>If you don't explicity specify a size for a container element, it will
    just take up as much space as its child elements need. An empty container
    will thus collapse to the size of a single point.</para>
    
  <para>A common mistake is to put only elements with percentual geometry values
    into a container. A child element with any percentual geometry value does
    <emph>not</emph> contribute to the container's size because its size or
    position itself is dependant on the container's size.</para>
    
  <para>With older versions of <application>gDesklets</application> the results
    of such a situation were undefined. With version 0.35,
    <application>gDesklets</application> switched to a more accurate geometry
    engine, and the container will collapse correctly.</para>
    
</section>



<section><title>Percentual Size</title>

  <para>Elements with their size given in percentages depend on the size of their
    parent container. A common mistake is to have a child's size depend on the size
    of a container which has no defined size, for example:</para>
    
  <programlisting><![CDATA[
  <display width="100" height="100">
  
    <frame>
      
      <group width="100%" height="100%" bg-color="white"/>
      
    </frame>
  
  </display>
  ]]></programlisting>

  <para>As you can seem the <command>group</command> element has it's size
    depend on the size of the <command>frame</command> container. This container,
    however, has no defined size. In that case it will collapse to fit its child
    elements. However, since the child element itself depends on the size of the
    container, the <command>frame</command> will collapse to a single point
    (see above).</para>
    
  <para>To make the <command>group</command> within the <command>frame</command>
    occupy the whole window area, the <command>frame</command> also needs to
    be stretched to the window size:</para>

  <programlisting><![CDATA[
  <display width="100" height="100">
  
    <frame width="100%" height="100%">
      
      <group width="100%" height="100%" bg-color="white"/>
      
    </frame>
  
  </display>
  ]]></programlisting>
          
</section>


<section><title>Relative Positioning</title>

  <para>Elements placed relatively to each other have to be in the same parent
    container. If this is not the case, it depends on the version of
    <application>gDesklets</application> whether this will raise an error or be
    silently ignored altogether.</para>

</section>

</section>
